hello welcome to psychology 230
personality and its transformations it's
called that because there are two things
that you have to take into account when
you're thinking about personality and
one of those is how personality stays
the same across time and that's really
what gives you your identity and what
allows you to identify other people and
then also how personality changes we're
going to discuss both those things from
a very large number of perspectives to
find out all the information that you
need for the course all you have to do
is type my name into a browser and
you'll get my home page which is the
page that you see here on the Left
there's a table of contents that says
current courses and then up here there's
also a table of contents that lists the
courses and this one's this one and then
this is the introductory page here and
then you can get to the course page like
this I don't really like blackboard so
I'm going to use this instead so this is
easy to get to and everything you need
to know about the course should be here
so we'll start with the very
straightforward things the first is
there's there's two sources for reading
in this course and one is a paperback
book which is called introduction to
personality and its transformations
they're both their chapters that I
selected from a classic personality
textbook that does a very good job of
covering classic personality theorists
although not such a good job of covering
more recent work the book was published
in 1982 Freud hasn't changed much since
night
- but there has been an awful lot of
personality research and so that brings
us to the second source of readings and
the second source of readings is
actually this web page so if you go down
the web page to lecture topics and
readings you'll see in the third column
a whole sequence of papers now you have
to pay attention to this lectures and
reading table more than anything else
because it tells you what's going on for
the for the duration of the course and
tell you what the lectures are so today
for example it's January 7th and so
we're doing an introduction and overview
maybe I can make that little bigger and
next week on Thursday we start with this
reading it's called free forms of
meaning in the management of complexity
and all you have to do is to get that
reading is click on it and then you get
that reading which is a fairly
straightforward process
um you would probably like the lectures
better if you do the readings beforehand
that's it isn't necessary you can do
this any way you want but you'll get
more out of the course I think if you do
that there's two TAS for this course
they're also listed here one is Vanessa
Ghosh and the other is Victor Swift
their availability is listed here so
Vanessa is available from 4:45 to 5:45
on Thursdays and Victor his mate is
available from 315 to 450 Tuesdays their
office offices are listed there as are
their email addresses so that you can
get in touch with them my office hours
are Wednesday from 4:15 to 5:45 now the
way I handle that is outside my office
which is office four zero four six which
is also listed there there are a number
of sign-up sheets that I'm just going to
post on the wall do that right after
class as they're printed out there's a
number of sign-up sheets that they're
listed on the wall and
your best bet is just to take a
15-minute slot don't take a whole bunch
of them because the student-to-teacher
ratio in this class is obviously quite
high and so just take one for now if you
would and maybe if you have a meeting
with me you can check back later to see
if there's time for another one I would
like to have more time than that
available but 90 minutes is what I can
spare this semester
so anyways they'll be up today now in
terms of the mechanics of the course
it's pretty straightforward there's no
tricks there's two midterms
the first one is February 6th and the
second one is March 13th and there's
also a final and the midterm in the
finals essentially make up 75% of the
course it's actually seventy seven point
five percent of the course but and then
there's two writing assignments the
first writing assignment is an essay and
the essay has a number of different due
dates so if you're on the website you
can go to writing assignments and then
you'll see all these different topics
that you could choose from now if you
click on one of these you get to this
little signup sheet here and then you
can put in your name and your email
address and that signs you up for that
topic and as you can see 10 people can
sign up for each topic so if you're in
love with a particular topic then you
should sign up sooner rather than later
the due dates fall a little after the
course content that's related to that
topic so it'll be the next class after
the lectures on that topic and and I've
spread them out across the year so that
the TAS don't die of frustration and so
that you guys can get your essays back
with a reasonable degree of promptness
hopefully within a week although let's
say two weeks which seems reasonable
so the second writing exercise which is
worth 7.5% the essays worth 15% is a
personality self analysis it's part of a
suite of programs that I designed called
the self authoring suite and I can show
you those and it's at self authoring
calm and I'll show you this video at
some point but for now there's
information here on these programs but
I'll give you code such a username and
password so that you can complete these
and what you'll be asked to do is to
complete an exercise that's based on a
Big Five model of adjectives description
of personality so since about 1930
statisticians have been studying the
structure of language at a sentence
level and add an adjective level to
determine what's the underlying
correlational structure of descriptive
phrases as they apply to human beings so
for example if you're happy you're
talkative and that might not be
surprising but the fact that those two
things are tightly connected was one of
the things that was discovered by the
factor analytic processes that led to
the development of the big five in the
big five they're roughly five traits as
the name might indicate extraversion
which is a positive emotion trait
neuroticism which is a negative emotion
trait agreeableness which is warmth and
empathy compassion the other side of
that is kind of a harsh coldness I guess
openness which is both intelligence and
creativity and conscientiousness which
is industriousness and orderliness now
there are virtues so to speak and fall
associated with all of those dimensions
so you could be too extroverted which
makes you rather impulsive and if you're
very extroverted it's more difficult to
get good grades in university because
you're always out having fun with your
friends and partying and that might be
good in that it'll help you develop a
fairly extensive social network which is
a useful thing if you're associated with
people who are useful for social
networking purposes but it can really
interfere with your ability to sit by
yourself and study if you're
conscientious that's a good predictor of
academic success because conscientious
people do what they say they're going to
do and they seem to suffer shame and
self-disgust and self-contempt and guilt
and so on if they don't if you get too
conscientious though you can get quite
boxed in and and orderly and narrow and
orderliness by the way seems to be
associated with great wing political
views and when it's extreme it starts to
get repressive and so the point of all
this is that there are five traits and
they have positive and negative aspects
especially at the extremes and these
programs are set up first of all so that
you'll see a series of adjectives that
are universal descriptors so it's
basically a small set of adjectives 100
to kind of cover each dimension of
personality with a reasonable degree of
comprehensiveness then you'll be asked
to pick which ones you think are
particularly relevant to you and then
you'll be asked to narrow that final
list in one half of the exercise a list
that represents your virtues and then in
the other half of the exercise a list
that represents your fault then you'll
be asked to describe a time when that
virtue played a positive role for you or
when that fault interferes with you and
then you'll be asked to describe how you
might capitalize on that virtue in the
future or perhaps bring that fall under
control in the future and it turns out
that writing exercises of this sort are
very practically useful they have a
variety of positive effects one of which
seen
to be an increase in academic
performance and our research so far has
indicated that that increase can be
quite substantial among with similar
programs at McGill we raised the
academic performance of struggling
University students by 25 percent so a
whole grade point and that a Business
School in Holland where this is being
studied in some depth we've studied
2,000 people they actually did the
future authoring program but not the
present authoring program which is the
one you're going to do and we improved
their overall academic achievement by
about 30 percent as well turns out that
articulating yourself is an
extraordinarily useful thing to do and
you could actually you could also think
about that more comprehensive way as the
goal of safe psychotherapy and
personality transformation a lot of
what's happening as you mature and
develop as a personality is that what
you are whatever that means I guess it's
your behaviors and your potential and I
don't know exactly what potential is but
your behaviors and your potential can be
increasingly organized at a high level
of consciousness articulated at a high
level of consciousness and articulation
is a funny word because partly it means
joint articulation you know your hands
are very articulated and that's why you
can do a lot of things with them and
hands and speech are very tightly
related which is why those peoples
speech centers are in the same
hemisphere as their dominant hand anyway
he's articulating yourself makes you
able to do many more things with
yourself and it also seems to quell your
negative emotion part because it's
clarifying you you know the more you
leave things muddy in your life the less
defined things are around you the more
active your stress response systems are
because if things are murky and
undefined your stress systems basically
assume that there are alligators and
snakes and predators hiding in all that
fog and gloom and that you're in a very
dangerous environment but if you clarify
that with careful attention and
articulation you can clear away the fog
and avoid
and that only leaves you with your
actual problems which once define
carefully you might find manageable an
example that would be you know when you
go into your room and you haven't done
your homework for a while and there's
piles of papers piling up or maybe
there's piles of junk on your computer
doesn't really matter and you'll have a
very powerful tendency to avoid that not
even to look at it right you don't even
want to look at it because it's and
that's chaos it's sort of growing in
your environment and there's a specific
part of your brain which evolved to
detect snakes that deals with such
little chaotic piles of undone business
and the more of those that are around
you psychologically or physically the
more negative emotion you experience the
less hope you experience and larger your
stress response chronically and that's
not good because if your stress response
is chronically elevated that suppresses
your immune logical function it makes
you overweight it predisposes you to
diabetes and cancer it makes you age
faster it increases the probability that
you'll have anxiety disorders and
depression it's a bad thing so so
clarifying who you are and what you're
doing is a good thing unless you want to
all those other things to happen which
seems highly improbable although people
desire some very strange things and
that's part of what we'll talk about as
this course progresses ok so if you want
to find out about the course you can go
to Jordan B Peterson calm and the
courses are listed there you can just
type my name in a search engine and
you'll find the courses
this course is psych 230 obviously I
mentioned if there's a reading book
which you have to buy the rest of the
readings are online the order that you
do that reading is listed on the
syllabus you also have to do two
assignments an essay which is only 750
words by the way but don't let that fool
you because a 750 word essay can be very
difficult to write the essay and then
this personality analysis now the
personality analysis all you have to do
is show it to the TA to show them that
you've completed
because we don't want to know what you
wrote down and we want to encourage you
to write down things that you know you'd
like to write down that are likely
private unless you want to broadcast to
the faults on Facebook which I suppose
you do after you complete exercise so
the reason I want you to do that what
was three reasons right one is well it
will familiarize you more with standard
models of personality because you'll
have to apply them to yourself and so
then you'll understand yourself better
too so that's a good thing and then it's
also a quasi clinical intervention and
some of you because you're in this
course are no doubt interested in
clinical psychology so this will give
you the flavor of the sorts of things
that a clinical psychologist might do
except a computer is doing it and then
which which turns out to be fine
people will actually often tell
computers things that they wouldn't tell
people yeah anyways and the third reason
is that well it should be good for you
and you know the education should be
good for you that's actually the purpose
of Education right it's supposed to make
you more healthy mentally and physically
it's supposed to make you more
productive and so that's what education
is for and that's what this class is for
so that's what we're aiming at so then
there's two exams two midterms 25% each
approximately there multiple-choice
I'll post sample questions so that
you'll know what they're like they're
not tricky people get worried about
exams and rightfully so but these aren't
tricky exams if you do the readings and
you come to the class the probability is
quite high that you'll do at least
reasonably well I don't ask you to
memorize dates and that sort of thing I
try to keep it at a conceptual level and
so the questions on the multiple-choice
tests are usually conceptual questions
where I try to get you to take something
that you've learned it read and to apply
it to the solving of a problem even
though they're in standard
multiple-choice format there's there's
usually not a tremendous number of
questions so you'll be able to complete
the exams in the time allows without any
trouble so now let's see I should tell
you guys who should take this course and
who shouldn't take it because you need
to know that since it's your first day
and so this course has two or three
aspects one aspect is is scientific that
really occupies the last half of the
course I would say in the purely
scientific part of the course with a
purely research oriented element of the
course so the first part of scientific
to because science has morning science
is more than mere testing of hypotheses
anyways the second half of the course
deals essentially with trade theory and
with psycho biology so what I want to do
is to tell you about the the basic
dimensions of human variability and also
how those are represented in the brain
so that you can make a connection and
and the body so that you can make a
connection between the theories and the
biological and cognitive substrates and
that sort of a unifying account so
you've got to be interested not if you
want to take this course and you know
and have it go well for you so there's
some psycho metrics that's the science
of measurement there's a little bit of
statistics there's a reasonable amount
of neuropsychology and some of its
complex some of it isn't but I try to
only pick things that I try to only pick
things to discuss with you that are
relevant at three levels to the analysis
I've looked them to be personally
relevant so that they tell you something
about yourself I want them to be
intellectually relevant but I also want
them to be culturally relevant so that
not all when you walk away from the
study not only do you know something
more about you and your friends but
hopefully you're a better functioning
creature in the broader social milieu so
so everything is picked to that end
including the psychobiological there
neuropsychological material in the trait
material there's a fairly hemp heavy
emphasis on clinical issues the first
half of the course deals with classic
theorists of personality
all the classic personality theorists
were clinicians now the U of T not
present doesn't have a clinical program
although they're starting it up in
Scarborough but down here it's a gorge
there's not many clinicians I think I'm
probably the only one I don't know why
they let me in and the the emphasis on
clinician that the emphasis of
clinicians is too full right one is well
who is the person or what is the person
but more importantly who could the
person be or what should they be and
that's a very strange thing about people
right I mean if you have a cat you don't
really sit around thinking what could
this cat be because it's a cat and you
know if it has an offspring they're
gonna be cats and in a thousand years
they're still gonna be just cats but
people well we're strange in ways that
are virtually overcome incomprehensible
and we're not only what we are but we're
also what we could be and in many cases
especially for people of your age you're
way more what you could be that what you
are and so focusing on what you could be
is an extremely important thing to do it
in fact there's there's plenty of
research and some of its associated with
the writing exercises that I've told you
about earlier that if you make efforts
to define who you could be and you know
in a way that you find interesting
because you might as well shape yourself
into something that you want to be that
that increases the efficiency with which
we work substantially it also makes you
a better person by reasonable measures
of better which sort of needs happier
than healthier you know more acceptable
or at least less repulsive to other
people so the clinical material is very
useful for that and the clinical
material is grounded in observation so
it's kind of like ethology ethology is
the study of animal behavior but not in
the labs observational study one of the
clinical stuff has this observation
quality to it it's heavily influenced by
philosophy if you're not interested
ideas this is a bad course for you
because it's it's it's a course that
private early concentrates on ideas I I
want them to have practical utility
because why not you might as well put
constraints on them but but the
fundamental focuses ideas and so when we
discussed the clinical material clinical
personality material will discuss the
philosophical background of that we'll
do the same thing when we get to the
cycle biological material so you want to
decide if you're not interested in
philosophical ideas then this is a bad
course if you're going to be stuck with
it with those sorts of things half the
time so and there's some old there's
some elements of the course they're
almost straight philosophy because some
of the clinical schools especially those
that were developed in the 1950s like
existential psychology are very tightly
associated with fields of philosophy
existentialism and phenomenology in that
case and so I think that sort of thing
is very much worth learning because it's
part of the history of ideas and you
should know something about it it's also
very interesting it's very useful to
know something about if you're gonna be
a clinical psychologist because you
should know a fair bit about a lot of
things if you're gonna be a clinical
psychologist but even if you're
interested in researching Sciences half
pipe hypothesis testing but the other
half is hypothesis generation that's the
most important out you got to think up
an idea before you can test it and you
know most of what you'll learn in the
methods class has nothing to do with
generating research hypotheses they just
tell you to do that first generate your
research hypotheses it's like yeah
that's the big problem right there the
resident is just
just brined it through this process and
the way you generate research hypothesis
is by knowing something and so you have
to learn a lot in order to generate a
research hypothesis that well first that
someone hasn't already else hasn't
already thought of and disproved which
is highly probable it's actually
depressing too
yeah the more and more knowledge because
what you find is that it everyone's
already thought of everything and most
your ideas are stupid so yeah so anyways
now let's see oh yes here's another
reason not to take the course there's a
lot of reading and there's less reading
there was last year I took out one paper
that was too hard I think it was too
hard for people even though it was a
great paper and but my right left the
rest of the day and so if you're looking
for a course with the light reading load
this isn't that course because this has
a heavy reading load now on the upside
for your essays and don't require you to
read outside the course you couldn't use
the material that's in the course to
write the essay so it's self-contained
but there's a lot of reading and it's
not easy reading and partly because a
lot of it is original papers all the
stuff that's listed on the web is
original papers and then the textbook -
it's a tough textbook it's mostly text
it doesn't have a lot of pictures in it
it has no stories at all about
celebrities I think that's the only text
left it doesn't have stories about
celebrities in it so if you're if you're
taking a tough course semester and you
don't have a lot of time to read then
well this isn't of course like that it's
of course where there's an awful lot to
read and the thing about the reading too
is that you have to think about it you
know like how fast you can read
something seems to be a function of how
complicated the words are that would be
function one
but the second function seems to be
something like how many ideas there are
per paragraph or maybe per page there
are lots of ideas per paragraph in these
readings that's why I picked them so you
can't just zip through them you have to
think about them well that's a good
thing if you do read them you'll know a
lot more at the end of the class then
you did it at the beginning of the class
and you'll find that that knowledge is
extremely useful I truly believe that
this knowledge can change your life well
that's what it was generated for right
it's generated by clinicians and
personality psychologists that's what
they're out there to do and they're out
there to take unrevealed potential that
could be anything into hammer it and
shape it into something that's hard and
pure and solid and you have to do a lot
of reading and writing but they need to
get to a point like that but it really
beats the hell of mucking about in the
murk and unfortunately that's how many
people live and I've seen the
consequences of that and if you spend
the next 30 years like that you will be
oh by the time you're 50 and so I
wouldn't recommend that so it's worth
doing the work it's really worth so
let's take a look now well first I'll
ask you if there are any questions yes
oh yeah I'll get the username and
passwords up to you pretty quick so I
just have to make contact with the guy
designed it with to get the code Seoul
won't be long I hope so
that's the plan some of you have
purchased it perhaps okay so it appears
that you can't there's also maybe some
old texts from write slag floating about
you can use those too so you can get a
good deal on them you can often get them
secondhand on Amazon for like 20 bucks
if you lure the old text is fine except
that it has more chapters in it but if
you pay attention careful attention to
the syllabus that won't be a problem
because all the chapters are numbered
and all you have to is match the number
on the syllabus to the number in the
book so other questions okay
so let's take a look at what we're going
to learn about lecture 2 so you can
think of human knowledge in some ways
just branching into two components you
can think of those two components as
knowledge about the subjective world and
knowledge about the objective world
that's one way of thinking about it
the other way you can think about it is
knowledge about what things are and
knowledge about what to do now most of
what you learn in the university is
knowledge about what things are but
that's only half of what you need to
know because you really need to know
what what you should go about and do
this is a real problem for human beings
because we're always trying to fit
having to think up what we should be
doing next and like that's the
fundamental question of life which is
well what should I do next or what
should i do tomorrow or what should I do
next week or next month or next year
because that's another problem about
being human is that not only do we have
to figure out what to do next but we can
also see the future or multiple futures
even and then we have to determine
those futures could be and how to avoid
others that we don't want to have come
into existence at all and then how to
configure our behavior so that as we
navigate through the potential futures
we land up more or less somewhere we
want and not somewhere we really don't
want and so that's a real problem what
that's an existential problem in fact
what that means is that we need
knowledge about the subjective and about
the behavior it's part of potential how
do you unravel yourself across time now
it's proved very difficult for human
beings to formalize that kind of
knowledge
now we formalize scientific knowledge
which is more knowledge about what
things are and about the objective world
the scientific method especially the
research method for analyzes our
knowledge about the objective world and
about what it's made of but it doesn't
give us much insight into what to do
about that all it seems to do actually
is increase our power to do things but
not necessarily to inform us as to the
direction in which that power should be
exerted and you don't really have to
look any farther than the 20th century
if you want historical proof of that
because as people got more and more
powerful so that we could sit in this
lovely classroom it will be warm and
cozy well it's terrible outside
we also learned how to kill each other
with unprecedented gusto and potency and
so science has enabled us on both sides
and that's how it is good or bad about
the behavioral side there's a tradition
of knowledge and it's an ancient
tradition and it's grounded in forms of
knowledge that are likely tens of
thousands of years old or maybe even
older than that and those are forms of
knowledge that are essentially
mythological or religious and the reason
that I start with those is first of all
religious systems are in many ways
theories of personality and there's very
tight associations between certain
religions of certain fields of
psychology so Judaism has been
identified fairly heavily with Freud and
Christianity with Carl Jung's work and
also with Carl
this was actually a seminarian and a lot
of the ideas about what a person could
be so these are ideas about the ideal
are derived from religious and
mythological substrates cuz you they
have to be derived from somewhere right
and so you think well how do people get
their ideas about what's possible or
what should be part of it's through
storytelling that's why you go to movies
right you go there to see what people
could be and you enact all those people
on the screen with your bodies well it's
happening and you have a little neural
system that does that so it puts you
rank the action it's an amazing ability
amazing human ability and the reason
we're so attracted to that sort of thing
is because we want to know what to do
with ourselves and there's a very large
body of very complex information that
pertains to that one of the things that
Carl Jung said was that what were the
things he believed was that that form of
knowledge have developed quite
explicitly up to about the time of the
Renaissance or rowboats at the time of
bacon and Descartes who founded and
Galileo who basically founded the
scientific method and then we sort of
start developing that kind of knowledge
and the knowledge of the objective world
just leapt ahead and in like
exponentially and so that's left us with
the same moral intelligence we have in
the 1700s but with 21st century
technology not necessarily a good thing
so part of what we're doing in a sense
is rescuing the past you know in my
other class sometimes I show Pinocchio
the movie how many of you seen Pinocchio
so yeah it's like the most popular
animated movie ever made seconds I think
there's a Lion King there's one scene in
Pinocchio and where Pinocchio rescues is
farther from a whale you may remember
that you may notice that you watch that
and that was perfectly fine as far as
you were concerned in fact that you
could watch a puppet swim with a cricket
to the bottom of the ocean and rescue
his father from a whale slain okay so
the first thing you might think about is
how in the world could you sit there and
swallow that and not even know she
noticed notice that you were doing
something as absurd and bizarre
any ritual you could possibly imagine
well it's it's partly because we're very
attracted to narrative and narratives
have structured narratives or about
behavior and they have a deep structure
and they have a deep symbolic structure
so for example the whale in Pinocchio
wasn't just any ordinary way over
because if you remember it also breathed
smoke and fire it's a very strange
behavior for a whale and not maybe even
a whale that strange and that made it a
dragon and so partly what that meant was
that Pinocchio was rescuing his father
from a dragon that's a very old story in
fact that story is the oldest story that
we have in written form it's a variant
of a story that was told by the
Mesopotamians about 5,000 years ago so
part of that story means when you should
rescue your father well from what well
from the murky chaos in which your
culture is embedded you know you guys
are all inheritors of rich cultural
traditions those are just words those
cultural traditions orient you they keep
you sane and if they're desiccated and
broken up and dead in archaic and lying
in the bottom of the chaos then you
better get them back out of there
because without of them you're gonna
live shallow and difficult lives and
that's a bad idea so starting with the
historical perspectives we can situate
ourselves in maybe some hundreds of
thousands of years of history maybe even
longer I can tell you in one manner when
it'd be longer it turns out that part of
the reason that we can see so well with
which we can human beings can really see
well way better than almost any other
animal except hunting birds hunting
birds can see better than us but other
than that it's us and that's especially
rare among mammals and particularly rare
among primates so you might ask yourself
well why can we see so well well it
turns out that part of the reason is
that we call evolved with predatory
snakes so predatory snakes are newer
than lizards by the way even though he
wouldn't think so
dan there's a woman at UCLA Dean Glynn
is Bell who was thinking why didn't
people see so well and so she wavered
she had the snake detection theory
because she worked with primates she
knew they could really see the sort of
camouflage patterns that snake hats
things have an emotion that they make
they're really good at detecting that
Plus human beings are very afraid of
snakes innately plus if you take
chimpanzees who've never seen a snake
and you throw a rubber snake in their
cage assuming they're in a cage then
they jump to the top of the cage and
because they're not happy about that
snake but then they look at it and then
if they're out in the jungle juggling
around and they see a baby snake then
they have a specific sort of pride they
mate and they'll stand there for like
nine hours watching a big snake making
this noise and all the other chimps
depending on how are afraid they are
also come and look at the snake and so
yeah because they want to know what that
snakes up to and that's what we want to
know - we want to know what the snakes
are up to that's for sure and the
circuit that we developed to detect
snakes the visual circuit is partly what
gives us such tremendous acuity of
mission part of the way Isabel figured
that out was by correlating primate
visual acuity with the prick and its
development over evolutionary time with
the prevalence of predatory snakes in
that geographical region and she found
that there was a very high correlation
so we can see sharply partly because
we're always looking for snakes and you
know that pile of undone homework in
your in your in your room that snakes as
far as the part of your brain that
develop to deal with snakes is conserved
and so you know if you leave a lot of
things I'm done around you then all
you've got is snakes and you're their
target and so that's no way to live and
so that whale down there at the bottom
the ocean that's kind of a variant of a
snake it's a dragon even though it's a
whale breathes fire right so let's call
it the Dragons and that's what it is and
the idea that you have to rescue
something from the dragon it's an
unbelievably old story and so that's
partly what we're gonna be doing at the
beginning of this course we're gonna be
going way back into the murk and mark of
prehistory
trying to understand what the hell we've
been up to for the last 60 million years
is that's when our tree-dwelling
ancestors first really started to deal
with predatory snakes and my suspicions
are that you're all evolved from one of
those little tree dwelling rats the
first one who figured out that if you
drop the snake a stick on a snake it
would probably run away so that's what
we've been doing for 60 million years
throwing sticks at snakes so that's the
first lecture and you'll see why when
you do the reading white this is broadly
relevant because it also accounts at
least in part for the human tendency to
demonize people who aren't like us
because it turns out that we use the
same circuit that we would use to handle
predatory reptiles let's say we use that
circuit to first process people who are
strange to us and it makes sense because
people who are strange to us who come
from different cultures and who
represent different high-heel are
unbelievably dangerous even though they
might also be unbelievably beneficial
you know the coordinating of Americans
they came out and they shook hands with
you Europeans and then 95% of them died
the next 150 years right they all died
in plagues they died of smallpox they
died of measles measles just wake them
up by the time the pilgrims came to
North America which is you know fairly
early in North American European history
95% of the Indians were already dead
they were welcomed in the Europeans
because they didn't have any people get
their crops off so meeting someone who's
strange is no trivial thing and even if
they don't poison me with some horrible
illness
they'll come along with some cockamamie
idea like Marxism and you'll be Chinese
and then it'll be the 20th century and a
hundred million of you will die it's
very useful to understand the deep
mythological structures that we live
inside and their relationship to our
brain in our body the reader gives you
insight into how people function it's
helpful the next lecture is on heroic
and shamanic initiation
and that brings us closer to the present
than say 60 million years ago it's more
like fifty thousand years ago there are
shamanic traditions all over the world
and the shaman has been a the precursor
to them to the to the to the man of
intelligence to the man of intellect the
man of culture and he's sort of a doctor
and a scientist and a priest all wrapped
up into one thing and he's often the
person who's in charge of the culture
many in many shamanic societies the
shaman has a vocabulary vocabulary that
vastly exceeds that of his peers and
that's because he's been taught it in
his initiatory process so that the
culture within which that particular
people survives can be transmitted down
the generations with very little error
people can remember things that are
transmitted verbally and preliterate
cultures with unbelievable accuracy and
then the shamanic initiation is very
intricate initiation as well are very
interesting processes because they
involve they involve death and rebirth
and death and rebirth is more or less
equivalent to change so here's something
to think about so if there's a mosquito
and it wants to make another mosquito it
basically lays 10,000 eggs right and
then all those eggs hatching 9999 of
those little mosquitoes die and that one
mosquito makes it in lays another 10,000
days so it's pretty costly reproductive
strategy right but so the way that
mosquito works is that it knows that the
world is chaotic and dangerous and it
has no idea how to survive in that so it
just makes a whole pile of mosquitoes
and it hopes that one of them will sneak
through and each of those mosquitoes is
a tiny bit different from each other
mosquito in terms of time and place and
also genetic structure and maybe one's
got some little advantage that allows it
to survive but it's costly right
it's 99999 to one otherwise we'd be
covered with mosquitoes so so the way
the mosquito deals with the fact
you can't figure out what's going on
it's by producing waters of mosquitoes
but the way people figure out what's
going on is by producing lots of ideas
and ideas are the relationship of ideas
to you and the external world is the
same as the relationship of animals to
the environment so there's a philosopher
in it
Alfred North Whitehead who said human
beings evolved to let their ideas die
instead of them now that's a smart way
of thinking because it means that you
can parse off a little some personality
of yourself maybe it's angry sub
personality or seven subpersonality or
an entertainer is then forward you know
know the earth exactly ideas they're
more like little spirits that are partly
you they're kind of stupid because
they've only got one direction but
there's still variants of you and maybe
you can present one of those to someone
which you might do if you're dating
someone who do you want to assuming you
still do that if you're dating someone
and you want to impress them maybe you
spin off some little variant of yourself
that you think is very attractive
probably won't work I don't work and if
it doesn't work well then you can get
all heartbroken and let it die and then
maybe the next one you spin off will be
a little more you know together and so
that's how people progress they progress
like dying and coming back to life at
different levels say I mean maybe you're
just taking some little ratty mistake
and so you can let it go and you're only
ashamed momentarily and it's only a
little pain when that circuit does or
maybe it's your whole damn personality
that has to go you know when that
happens to people when they encounter a
catastrophe of one form or another so
that might happen to someone close to
you dies or if you lose a limb or if you
get an illness or you know any of the
horrible things that plague people to
very deep levels which might be pretty
much all of you has to go and maybe
you'll actually die but if you don't
well you can let go what's holding you
back and maybe that's your old self and
then you can come back to life and I'll
tell you it's a lot better to do that
voluntarily before it's necessary than
involuntarily in a moment of crisis and
I
say in some ways that's the lesson of
clinical psychology confront the damn
snakes first because other it's really
hard to get out of their bellies once
they beat you so the shaman the shamanic
initiation czar death and rebirth
initiations they formalize that they're
often the the rituals themselves are
often accompanied by the use of
different process of blues legends which
for one reason or another seem to
facilitate at least symbolically
the process of transformation from life
to death and back to life so they're
dramatizations of the process by which
people learn you learn something to
really learn some presupposition that
you had before that has to crumble and
then the new information comes in and
you can build a new self around it but
that's a painful process and that's part
of why people stick to their ideas or
their past selves you know what you
could stick to your past self and I
would be fine except that everything's
changing around you all the time and so
if you don't change then you just get
more and more outdated you're more and
more archaic none of your
presuppositions work anymore and so
you're like you like this rusty machine
clanking around running into things all
the time and your life is very miserable
because you don't fit the environment
anymore and so when I talk about
personality and its transformations
something that you could ask yourself
which is in some way the most
fundamental question you can ask
yourself is are you the thing that stays
the same or are you the thing that
changes and you know the thing that
changes can live in a lot more places
and so that's worth thinking about it
but the cost is well when you change you
die a little bit and that's painful or
maybe you die a lot and that's really
painful so if you ever wonder why people
don't change that's part of the reason
then we the next section is on
constructivism we're gonna talk mostly
about the essays
developmental psychologist I like Piaget
a lot because BJ had an interesting
question is which is it's not a genetic
question or an environmental question
you know you might think those are the
only two kinds of questions there are
when you think about it's not exactly
that here's why it's not clear to what
degree you're specified by your genes so
here's one possibility so let's say that
it coated in your genetic structure our
whole variety of potential use like who
knows how many oh the potential used
that the entire history of mankind has
been able to weave into their genetic
structure they're all sitting down there
it coded in your genes and then that
very complex structure that's rife with
potential pops up into a particular
environment and then it interacts with
that environment like a program
interacts with the computer and gathers
information of one form or another that
takes that information and the material
that it interprets and builds the real
you out of them and that's what Piaget
was stunned he was trying to figure out
how is a child go about taking itself
from you know this thing that just lays
there squats basically to something
that's you know you go on YouTube but
you see what people can do what human
beings can do it's plenty unbelievable I
mean we're so ridiculously versatile
people can do things that are just
impossible in every dimension
intellectually physically spiritually
they can even eat hot dogs that a rate
that you can hardly imagine
we're very variable and Piaget was very
interested in trying to figure out how
all of that embodied variability to come
out of this little package of potential
at the beginning of life it's very
interesting
so that's constructivism how does the
individual construct him or herself from
nothing in some ways from birth forward
and so Piaget especially his discussion
of isn't developed it's sort of like the
analysis of the unfolding of a human
being it because people were to do one
full till you know because babies when
they're born don't crunch it up like
this you know get going and that was Phe
is concerned so so that's that's good
and then we go from there to depth
psychology
you might think about that Morris
psychoanalysis now people have people
aren't very happy generally speaking
about psychoanalytic theory especially
if their research oriented but there's a
variety of reasons for that and one of
them is they don't know anything about
it that would be the first reason people
are often tempted to denigrate anything
they don't understand it's actually
quite hard to understand the
psychoanalytic thinking it's in fact
it's very hard and the other thing about
scientists and research scientists who
engaged into psychological work is
they're actually usually fairly mentally
healthy you know at least they're
healthy enough to be scientists which
you know you've got to be pretty healthy
to be a scientist to go to be
disciplined what if you get up and go to
work every day you have to be able to
think about complex things you have to
be very orderly and persistent you know
and so if there's a lot of demand on you
if you're a scientific researcher so the
promis scientific researches they hang
around with other scientific researches
then they think that's what human beings
are like and human beings are nothing
like scientific researchers there are a
tiny minority of the population there is
bizarres like albino Buffalo and to
think of them as representative of human
is insane first of all most people have
IQs in the 99th percentile so it's like
why bother even thinking about them
normal human beings are very weird
especially the ones that don't function
well and not functioning well is a
bottomless pit though that's what hell
is important by the way it's not
functionally well it's a bottomless pit
and if you're dealing with people who
aren't functioning well one of the most
mysterious things is how they can take a
situation is god-awful beyond your worst
imaginings and then think up three or
four creative ways to make it worse and
if you're dealing with someone like that
and you do if you're a clinician if
you're dealing with someone like that
good luck with your behavioral
interventions man that's like throwing
sticks at an elephant you're just not
gonna get anywhere and one of the ways I
want to demonstrate this to you I'm
gonna show you a film called crumb
crumbs a harsh film but it's the best
documentary by the way underground comic
named Robert Crumb who's actually quite
a genius even though he's perverse in
precisely the Freudian ways that are
interesting and his brothers are even
worse so I'll walk you through that
because I can't figure out any other way
of giving you a taste of what Freud is
psychopathology is like it's not pretty
and that's the other reason that sort of
clean minded research scientists don't
like psychoanalytic thinking because
it's really in many ways it deals with
the most disgusting elements of human
behavior and so it's not even that
pleasant to think about and then there's
you who we'll talk about after Freud and
Jung is so strange that he makes Freud
look normal and you believed that as I
mentioned earlier believed that there is
a universal grammar of ethics of
morality it's not arbitrary it's not
relative you know in the Universities
the theory has been at least since the
1960s that one person's ethics is as
good as another person and there's no
way of distinguishing
reliably between them well I
I think that's absolutely nonsense it's
also extremely dangerous nonsense and I
also think there's no evidence for it
whatsoever because we now know a lot
about Cuban universals which are aspects
of human behavior that are constant
across all cultures and there are a lot
of them there are a lot of them now the
other thing is there's just not that
many ways that half-mad primates can
gather together in large groups and live
productively it's not easy if you think
of all the civilization work that went
into allowing all you people from all
these different cultures to sit here in
peace and comfort it's mind-boggling if
you think there's a million ways to do
that well think again maybe there's one
way to do that you know what we do it
well enough so here we are and no one's
being knifed so so that's you and he's
profound beyond belief really beyond
belief so that's those guys all dealt
with unconscious unconscious means and
so I can give you a bit of a hint it's
partly the information that's coded in
your behavior so for example there are a
lot of things that you can do with your
body that you don't know how you do or
how do you ride a bike or how you talk
you can talk but you don't know how you
talk you just move your mouth I hope but
you get the point right you have no
conscious apprehension whatsoever of the
micro details that are necessary to
allow you to move your mouth so there's
a lot of information encoded in you that
you don't have conscious access to and
it's not only physiologically in code
it's also culturally in decoded because
you've been targeted and shaped by the
interactions of all the people you've
ever encountered and they in turn by all
the people they have ever encountered
including their ancestors so you're the
product of this unbelievably complex
multi-generational exchange of
information that in some ways is all
about how to make you acceptable to the
public and there's only certain ways you
be acceptable to the public you know you
have to be relatively clean for example
at least in our society you can't be too
boring or you won't have any friends
you also can't be too exciting you know
you can't be too violent you can't be
too empty-headed unless you're
associating the people who like to feel
superior you know there's there's we put
a lot of demands on each other in terms
of what constitutes acceptability let
alone ideal we're always telling each
other about both of those what's
acceptable what's ideal every
interaction you have shapes you into an
approximation of acceptable and ideal
and that's why we coded in you - it's
encoded in your behavior it's also
encoded in your imagination and that's
why you can go to the movie and you can
instantly identify the hero and the
villain which is of course the first
thing you do when you go to the movie
because otherwise it makes sense of it
and so that encoding prior to
articulation that's all the unconscious
and that's what the psycho analysts were
interested in Emily's now the cognitive
neuroscientists have kind of got there
too but they're still deluded into
thinking that what's in your head is
information and that it's ideas and
those are sort of cold and dead things
and your head is not full of ideas and
information
it's full of Devils and snakes and the
psychoanalyst knew that and by that I
mean you're alive and so are your
subcomponents and all your little sub
personalities and I'm just ideas they
see they think hear it feel it have a z'
as you know for example when you get
possessed by anger the aim can be
entirely destructive I want to bring
down the person I love half an hour
later you think what the hell was I
thinking about like yeah no kidding
well you weren't thinking you're just
possessed by a little some personality
and that's what the psycho analysts were
interested in subpersonality fantasies
next we go to the humanists in the
existentialist now they're interesting
because they come at the problem of
what's wrong with people from a kind of
Universalist perspective now for Freud
if you weren't sick you were healthy and
that seems obvious
because you think you can make a clear
distinction between sex and healthy but
the existentialists they didn't want any
of that their hypothesis was if you're
human you're sick there's no way out and
the reason you're saying is that life
itself poses a paradoxical problem to
you partly because you're so conscious
and because you're self-conscious and
actually a sequence of paradoxical
problems a how do you live when you're
vulnerable and mortal that's a rough way
because you might say well why should I
born at all who's gonna know anyways in
a thousand years or a million years or
why is there suffering or how do you go
on in the face of cruelty and those are
questions that drip that people's soul
and crush it and they're not a
consequence of mental illness it's like
what how long should it take you to
recover if your whole family is wiped
out in a car accident what's healthy
well we don't know the answer to that
it's like should you ever recover maybe
if you were half ways empathic would
just kill you you know a lot of times
people can't recover from their grief
because they're guilty they say how can
i how can I live when know all those
people close to me died and they died
unfairly
that's an existential problem and then
there's one class which is vulnerability
and mortality
everyone's not that stereo so how you
deal with that hard question second
class of problems well everybody's
always evaluating always and you're
never good enough
so what that means is that you're always
in an insufficient relationship with
society and history no matter how good
you get it's not good enough and so
history itself as well as culture always
faces you as a judge and so that's the
second category of the existential
problem then the third problem is well
what to do about you yourself you know
there's nature you have to
there's culture you have to contend with
and then you've got yourself and your
self-consciousness and your deep
knowledge of all the things about you
that could really use some repair and
the thing about those problems is that
everyone has them and they always have
them and as far as we know they always
will and so they're built into the
condition of being human and that's what
existentialism is about it's like life
is a paradoxical problem is there any
possible solutions to a paradoxical
problem well that's that's that's in
some ways the question of the meaning of
life and one hint is that well what's
the meaning of life and one answer to
that is this is the hint is that the
meaning to life is the pattern of
thought an action that you take that
enables you to tolerate at least
tolerate the conditions of life and then
maybe you could move one step beyond
that if you're feeling a little
optimistic and saying the meaning of
life is the pattern of conception in
action that enables you to welcome the
conditions of life and then you might
ask you something is there such a mode
of being given the nature of the problem
that you have to contend with is there
actually a mode of being that would
enable that you could say the
vulnerability the judgment the
insufficiency it's worth it under these
conditions and that's the other
existential question and the people who
posed those questions
they weren't messing around you're going
to read people like Franco Viktor Frankl
and then tell examiner's Solzhenitsyn
and what those two people lived through
I mean it's unimaginably horrible and
when they were wrestling with the
questions that I just described
they weren't academic they weren't
academic issues they were embodied
issues of life and culture and genocide
and cruelty and so their examination of
that had to be deep enough to be able to
contend with questions like that and
answers that are deep enough to contend
with questions like that are frightening
answers when we have Reading Week it
would be a relief
the last part of the course this is when
we switch over to the more scientific
domain and so we're gonna do two things
as I said we're going to take a pretty
deep look at how the brain functions as
far as we know in our current state of
unimaginable ignorance like we're we
really know so little
maybe we know I've been a little bit
about the brain but we certainly don't
know anything yet about consciousness
the consciousness seems to be a very
well it's a relevant part of the brain
right it's sort of the part that
everybody cares about this is
consciousness in some sense seems to be
you even more than your brain is you I
mean your brain is just this thing
inside your skull but your consciousness
you know that's your being we don't have
a clue about consciousness I are
scientific we're not even needed to
conceptualize it it's a real mystery so
but having said that there's still
plenty of things that are interesting to
do about the brain one of the things
we're going to do and this is sort of
associated with the Freud's idea of the
end you know the end for Freud was the
natural self and so that was your
primordial you could think about them as
drives or dedications or or values
values is probably the most doctor and
their sexuality those are the talk to
Freudian serves there's plenty others
eating Freud didn't care about that we
do now because everyone has an eating
disorder or virtually everyone so for
the Victorians it was sexuality for us
it's food sex doesn't seem to be a
problem but we just can't eat anymore so
we're going to take a look at the
low-level biological systems in the
brain and those are systems God some of
those systems are so old that even
crustaceans have them so for example
this is so cool so if you give a logs
truths being defeated in a dominance
fight because they fight for dominance
and they might even know it if you mean
the lobster if you take a lobster who's
been defeated in the dominance dispute
the bowl
- his little lobster hole and poked and
wouldn't be when he's piloting he gets
all collapse and you can't even really
get him out of his hole with a stick
because he's gonna sit in there you know
be upset about his darlings defeat and
leave you go come on this is kind of a
new lobster already go yeah and maybe
not if you take that same monster and
you give him antidepressants right after
he fights he won't go back into his cave
and hide and you'll fight right away
again and so you think that that means
that the circuitry that underlies our
defeat related depression is 300 million
years old and even crustaceans have it
so that's way down in your brainstem man
cuz lobsters hardly even have brains in
fact if the lobsters been talking he's
being a dog lobster for a long time and
he gets defeated badly then when he goes
off to pout he has to dissolve his whole
brain it's all he does his dominance
stop then he grows a new subordinate
brain weasels around so and that's
useful to think about the next time you
really get defeated because all that
pain you're going through it's like
you've got some circuit repairs to make
and if you'd be badly defeated well
maybe you should just let yourself
collapse and all that stuff clear away
so that you could come back
so that's low level to stuff brain stem
stuff it's way down at the bottom of
your being at home but we're gonna talk
about systems that are above that too
but still low with a hypothalamus for
example it's a very cool brain area it's
sort of responsible for all the basics
rods hunger temperature regulation
sexuality defensive aggression predatory
aggression looks like it's something
different everyone has those systems you
know so they're like these sub beings
that live inside us but there are also
preconditions for communication
you know because you might say to your
friend I'm angry today and your friend
doesn't say well what do you mean angry
he says well what happened to upset you
because he knows what anger meanings and
the reason he knows that is cuz he's
already got it in his head he's liked
you he gets angry it's
it's afraid their basic emotions but not
only the basic emotions but the basic
motivations and so we're going to look
at the brain systems that underlie the
basic motivations and the basic emotions
and in some sense those systems are
equivalent to the physiological
incarnation of the in that Freud
described at the end of the nineteenth
century and so that's a nice way to look
at it you'll go through the
psychoanalytic thinking which which kind
of puts flesh on these systems because
for the psychoanalyst and this is why
they're still relevant those weren't
just systems they were living
personalities narrow one-eyed
personalities then we want one thing but
personalities nonetheless ancient gods
that's another way of looking at and
things you have to connect begin with
whether you believe in them or not we'll
discuss all five traits as well
extraversion as I said that's positive
emotion neuroticism that's negative
emotion people vary on those dimensions
agreeableness that seems to be
associated with the maternal behavior on
one hand and predatory hunting on
another to see what thieves are hunters
and mammals it's a weird combination
right because if you're a hunted animal
you have to figure out how not to kill
and eat your children right and that
happens in lots of mammalian species
especially among the males so they have
to be moved away but he would beings
have solved that more or less you know
it gets complicated in mixed families
because if you're the child of a
stepparent
you have 100 times the likelihood of
being abused so we'll talk about
conscientiousness which is a great
predictor of long-term life success but
also associated with fascist political
priests predispositions because it turns
out that the way you vote has very
little to do with what you pay and very
much to do with what your temperament is
so even for high level cognitive
functions like political belief these
underlying systems play a determining
role last two things we're going to talk
about performance prediction and by that
I mean well
there's been accruing evidence you might
say what what be what how do you have a
happy life first of all I would say
that's a stupid question but we'll go
because happiness isn't it's not the
right name it's it's a way it's not a
place to go it's a it's a manner of
manifestation while your journey it's
something like that leaving that aside
what do you need to live a high quality
life well we kind of know that already
I mean it's kind of obvious you need
friends need intimate relationships you
need meaningful work you know have any
more money than will pay your bills
doesn't help that much
etc it's like you know it's like
intelligent moderation of discipline
it's very boring
it's exactly what you'd expect if you
were pessimistic about excitement
performance prediction we're going look
very carefully at the nature of the
traits that make people successful in
life and you know you might say well
what do you mean by successful you know
one of the things I mean is not in too
much pain and anxiety does that turns
out to actually be more important to
people than being happy you know what
you say to people what do you want they
say they want to be happy but if you
analyze what they mean by happy they
mostly mean not suffering and not
terrified you get those two things under
control like the worst that can happen
to you is that you'll be bored so and
then we'll wrap it up at the end ok so
that's the course so I'm glad to be
teaching it it's good to see all of you
here it looks like you're trying to have
a comfortable classroom so that's kind
of nice decide if you decide if you want
to take the course because I don't want
you to be disappointed and so I'm really
really telling you seriously you got
like the ideas if you like this lectures
you like the course and you got to do
the read and there's a fair bit of read
so
we'll see you Thursday
[Applause]